Alright, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, welcome to דף יומי Daf Yomi מסכת
שבועות. Masechet Shavuot. We're in the exciting, at the end of the
exciting first chapter, and we're at the bottom of דף י"ג עמוד
ב', Daf Yud-Gimmel Amud Bet,
10 lines from the wide lines in the bottom.
The discussion we're having is what atones for the כהנים. Kohanim. We
know that ישראל Yisrael atones with the שעיר, Se'ir, the goat, and
we're not sure if the כהנים Kohanim are included in it or
not. We have two different opinions: רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks that when the שעיר
Se'ir atones for ישראל, Yisrael,
and it says בעד אשר לעם, Ba'ad Asher La'am, for the people,
that means everybody, כהנים Kohanim included. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon thinks no,
the כהנים Kohanim are going to be atoned, they're going to have
כפרה kappara differently. I don't know if you like this metaphor, I
might get into trouble for it, but
thinking about what Rabbi Linzer said, like this is like a major
purifying place, right? Or like the whole כפרה kappara issue, I don't
know if I mentioned it here before, the image that came to
my mind is like a city sewage plant. Okay,
thank you. All the water comes to one place, and now we're
in the last spot that we have to clear this up, and
if we don't clear up that last spot, the water we're going
to funnel back into the system is not going to be clean,
is not going to be usable. So, take it or leave it
as good as it is, but yeah.
I didn't know if you saw the illustration behind you. That lower
part is the פר, Par, and these are the two goats.
I saw this in the outline when he was drawing
it. That's the כהן, Kohen, and so the כהנים Kohanim have the
פר, Par, but
and the people have the שעיר. Se'ir. But we have not quite
determined where is that line. And this is what we're dealing in
the next few lines with a ברייתא Baraita and a couple of
discussions. Is the פר Par just for אהרן, Aharon, because it says
וכיפר בעדו Vichipper Ba'ado for him? Is the פר Par for אהרן
Aharon and his immediate family, or will the כהנים, Kohanim, I'm giving
you the punchline, will the כהנים Kohanim be included in אהרן's Aharon
family? Therefore, that funnel, you know if you picture all the חטאים,
chata'im, whatever, all the mistakes,
flowing to this cleansing operation, we now have the עם Am going
to the שעירים, Se'irim, and we have another funnel coming of the
כהנים, Kohanim, and we're not sure yet where it's going. Is it
going here or is it going here? We know אהרן Aharon is
coming here, the people are coming here, what about the rest of
the כהנים? Kohanim? This is where I think we stopped, this is
where we are right now. So we're in the bottom of י"ג
ב'.
Yud-Gimmel
Bet. The section begins with מן תנא להא דתנו רבנן Man Tana
Lehade-Tanu Rabbanan and we're going to have a ברייתא Baraita that's going
to try to explain it, then the גמרא Gemara is going to
review the ברייתא Baraita and look at it as one option and
then we'll still have a couple of other options how to understand
that split. Where
are
the חטאים chata'im of the כהנים Kohanim going to go? Okay, so
we have a פסוק: pasuk: ושחט את שעיר החטאת אשר לעם, Veshachat
Et Se'ir Hachattat Asher La'am, it's in ויקרא Vayikra 16:15,
that he will slaughter the goat of the sin offering אשר לעם,
Asher La'am, of the people. We'll hear that construct repeating again and
again as we're trying to unpack: what is this term אשר לעם?
Asher La'am? The understanding is that it's what is called a מיעוט,
mi'ut, it is exclusionary,
and it excludes אהרן, Aharon, Aaron the High Priest, and all the
priests, all the כהנים. Kohanim. So then the גמרא Gemara continues and
said שאין הכהנים מתכפרים בו. She'ein HaKohanim Mitkaperin Bo. So that means
the כהנים Kohanim have no כפרה, kappara, this is not how they
can purify. ובמה מתכפרים בפרה של אהרן. Ubame Mitkaperin? Beparo Shel Aharon.
So they'll be purified. side with Aaron's bull. It would have been
nice if the section just ended here, but now we're going to
have a few opinions back and forth in order to eventually come
to the same point at the end. יכול לא יתכפרו
בפרהו של אהרן Yachol lo yitkapru b'paro shel Aharon שהרי כבר נאמר
אשר לו she'harei kvar ne'emar asher lo מעתה אין להם כפרה. me'ata
ein lahem kapparah. There is a possibility that this bull is not
good for all the כהנים Kohanim because about the bull it says
specifically אשר לו asher lo which is to him. If it's to
him then we have a how do you say how do you
call it like an area in between you know between the two
fences right the people and אהרן Aharon are the כהנים. Kohanim. What
are we what are we doing with it?
אבל Aval at the end... it doesn't say אבל Aval I'm putting
this in...
מעתה אין להם כפרה me'ata ein lahem kapparah so possibly they have
no atonement. כשהוא אומר יכפר על הכהנים מצינו להם כפרה. K'she'hu omer
yichaper al ha'Kohanim matzinu lahem kapparah. So if you look at the
end of that section in אחרי מות Achrei Mot that we read
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur there's a whole list of everybody who
gets atoned.
Let me just quickly find it.
The last פסוק pasuk it
says וכיפר את מקדש הקודש ואת אוהל מועד ואת המזבח יכפר ועל
הכהנים ועל כל עם הקהל יכפר. V'chiper et mikdash ha'kodesh v'et ohel
moed v'et ha'mizbe'ach yichaper v'al ha'Kohanim v'al kol am ha'kahal yichaper. So
therefore it says מפורש meforash in the תורה Torah that the כהנים
Kohanim will be atoned for. So
where is it? אהרן Aharon says
אשר לו, asher lo, the people says אשר לעם. asher la'am. What
about that middle water, the כהנים? Kohanim?
Okay.
So we know that somewhere they have a כפרה. kapparah. במה הן
מתכפרים? Bameh hen mitkaprin? מוטב שיתכפרו בפרהו של אהרן שהרי הותר מכללו
אצל ביתו ואל יתכפרו בשעיר הנעשה בפנים שלא הותר מכללו אצל ביתו.
mutav she'yitkapru b'paro shel Aharon she'harei hutar miklalo etzel beito v'al yitkapru
b'sa'ir ha'na'aseh bifnim she'lo hutar miklalo etzel beito. Okay, what do we
mean? We say the שעיר sa'ir has no exclusion, it says specifically
אשר לעם. asher la'am. The פר, par, the bull, has an exclusion,
it says אשר לו asher lo for אהרן. Aharon. We will see
that the ברייתא baraita and the גמרא Gemara open it up to
understand that אשר לו asher lo for אהרן Aharon and then it
says אשר לו ולביתו, asher lo u'v'beito, his household. Therefore the כהנים
Kohanim are also going to be considered אהרן's Aharon household and they
are also going to be atoned with the with the bull. ואם
נפשך לומר, V'im nafshacha lomar, and if you need yet another proof,
הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, it brings us a פסוק pasuk
from תהילים, Tehillim, great הלכתית halachic proof, בית אהרן ברכו את ה'
בית הלוי ברכו את ה' יראי ה' ברכו את ה'. Beit Aharon
barchu et Hashem Beit Ha'Levi barchu et Hashem Yirei Hashem barchu et
Hashem. So
we have a פסוק pasuk that divides the people, right, the nation
into three sections, בית אהרן, Beit Aharon, בית הלוי, Beit Ha'Levi, and
יראי ה', Yirei Hashem, which does not mention כהנים Kohanim at all.
So where are the כהנים? Kohanim? The כהנים Kohanim are included in
that בית אהרן. Beit Aharon.
In your free time if you want to see
תוספות Tosafot will ask in the next page
not the question of what happens to the כהנים Kohanim but if
we have כפרה kapparah for the people and for the כהנים Kohanim
or for אהרן Aharon and his family, what happens to the לויים?
Levi'im? Where is the כפרה kapparah for the לויים? Levi'im? And where
is that going is more of a question than where are the
כהנים Kohanim going.
Okay, so now somebody said for תוספות Tosafot they should be with
the Israelites. Yes, the לויים. Levi'im.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. But as they're not for תוספות Tosafot that's a
question as we are dealing specifically with העם ha'am and הכהנים. ha'Kohanim.
I wonder if like you know how much power prestige and all
that is going into that discussion of where where are the לויים.
Levi'im. You're like with the כהנים Kohanim but not quite when it
comes to atonement you go with the people not with us kind
of. There's a little bit over there. Okay, so that was the
ברייתא. baraita. We haven't yet transferred it to to the גמרא. Gemara.
מאן תנא? Man tanna? The question is who teaches us this section
that we just read?
אמר רבי ירמיה דלא כרבי יהודה. Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah d'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda.
Okay, this cannot be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda said that the כהנים Kohanim are going to be atoned for
with ישראל, Yisrael, right?
דאי רבי יהודה אמר כהנים יש להם כפרה בשעיר המשתלח. D'ei Rabbi
Yehuda amar Kohanim yesh lahem kapparah b'sa'ir ha'mishtale'ach. ומני? Umani? So who
can it be?
רבא אמר רבי שמעון היא דאמר כהנים אין להם כפרה בשעיר המשתלח.
Rava amar Rabbi Shimon hi d'amar Kohanim ein lahem kapparah b'sa'ir ha'mishtale'ach.
So it must be that this is a ברייתא baraita that we
got from רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon because he said that the כהנים
Kohanim are not going to be atoned for by the... scapegoat, right?
By the שעיר המשתלח. seir ha-mishtaleach. Therefore, this must be his explanation.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אפילו תימא. afillu teima. אביי Abaye says there's
a way to explain this in accordance with רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
opinion.
And this is what it's saying: רבי יהודה הכי קאמר, Rabbi Yehuda
hachi ka-amar, מעתה אין להם כפרה בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו. me'ata ein lahem
kaparah be-tum'at mikdash ve-kodashav. כשהוא אומר, kshehu omer, יכפר על הכהנים, yechaper
al ha-kohanim, מצינו שיש להם כפרה בשאר עבירות. matzinu she-yesh lahem kaparah
bi-sh'ar aveirot. Maybe this is talking about,
maybe this is talking about other transgressions, not about the specific transgressions
we've been dealing with of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tum'at mikdash ve-kodashav, the
impurity of the temple and the holy things and the meat that
we're eating at the משכן. mishkan.
חכה רגע, chakeh rega,
וכמו דמצינו שיש להם כפרה בשאר עבירות
כך יש להם כפרה בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו. u-kmo de-matzinu she-yesh lahem kaparah
bi-sh'ar aveirot kach yesh lahem kaparah be-tum'at mikdash ve-kodashav. So just like
we found that they're included in the atonement of other transgressions,
so they have an atonement with the, they have an
atonement, sorry, they have an atonement in the טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tum'at
mikdash ve-kodashav, in the impurity of the מקדש mikdash and the קדשים
kodashim and the meat eaten there. במה הם מתכפרים? bameh hem mitkaprim?
What would their atonement be?
מוטב שיתכפרו בפרו של אהרן שהרי הותר מכללו אצל ביתו. motav she-yitkapru
be-paro shel Aharon she-harei hutar mi-klalo etzel beito. One second.
It's better, in the middle of a coughing fit, I need some
water. It's better that they would be atoned with the bull of
אהרן Aharon because that was already excluded from its specificity because it
says אצל ביתו, etzel beito, his household. ואל יתכפרו בשעיר שנעשה בפנים
שהרי לא הותר מכללו. ve-al yitkapru ba-seir she-na'asa bifnim she-harei lo hutar
mi-klalo. About the שעיר seir we mentioned which we just brought in
the ברייתא braita and we mentioned that the שעיר seir is only
אשר לעם asher la-am
and there's no exclusion for it to include the כהנים. kohanim. This
is going to be some session. Okay. ואם נפשך לומר, ve-im nafshach
lomar, הרי הוא אומר: harei hu omer: בית אהרן ברכו את ה'
beit Aharon barchu et Hashem etcetera. If you still have questions,
we have a פסוק pasuk from תהילים Tehillim which we just quoted
at the bottom of י"ג. yud-gimmel. בית אהרן ברכו את ה', בית
הלוי ברכו את ה', יראי ה'
ברכו את ה'. beit Aharon barchu et Hashem, beit ha-Levi barchu et
Hashem, yirei Hashem
barchu et Hashem.
We see the three groups:
Aaron's household, the Levites, and the people. Therefore, the כהנים kohanim are
not mentioned and we understand the כהנים kohanim are included with בית
אהרן. beit Aharon. ומה אם נפשך לומר? u-mah im nafshach lomar? וכי
תימא ביתו כתיב? ve-chi teima beito ktiv? כולם קרויים ביתו. kulam keruyim
beito. What we just explained, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, בית
אהרן ברכו
את ה', יראי ה' ברכו את ה'.
beit Aharon barchu et
Hashem, yirei Hashem
barchu
et
Hashem. והאי אשר לעם
להכי הוא דאתא.
ve-hai asher la-am le-hachi hu
de-ata. And that's for whatever is for the people,
what does it,
with regards to the אשר לעם, asher la-am, right? To the goat
that is mentioned, the שעיר seir that is for the people,
what does it teach us? Does it teach us what the ברייתא
braita said, that the priests don't get atonement through it and that
they need the bull? המיבעי ליה דקאמר רחמנא מי דעם ליהוי. ha-mibaye
lei de-ka-amar rachmana mi de-am le-hevi. It's just for the
people
and not for the כהנים. kohanim. ההוא טומאת עדת בני ישראל נפקא.
ha-hu tum'at adat bnei Yisrael nafka. That is for
what
we just explained, this is from
ויקרא Vayikra
right here and this is for the people.
One second, let me...
So you get it from a different פסוק, pasuk, you don't need
it from this one. That's what he's asking, right?
From this we saw just a minute ago
the beginning, yes, the beginning of this section in אחרי מות Acharei
Mot
16:5. Sorry.
Okay. והיה אשר לו Vehaya asher lo
ההוא טומאת עדת ישראל. hahu tumat Adat Yisrael. Yeah, והיה אשר לו
vehaya asher lo להכי הוא דאתא. lehachi hu de-ata.
גמרא, Gemara, sorry, the גמרא Gemara asks again question and with regard
to this phrase that the next פסוק pasuk that's stated in ויקרא
Vayikra 16:6, does it come to teach what the ברייתא baraita teaches,
that it atones only for Aaron's transgressions, not for the transgressions of
the others? האי
מיבעי ליה לכדתניא Hai miba lei lekadatanya משלו הוא מביא ואינו מביא
משל ציבור. mishelo hu mevi ve-eno mevi mishel tzibur. So we'll see
that there is a discussion at the
we had it in יומא, Yuma, right? We had it in יומא.
Yuma.
In יומא. Yuma. That it says
the phrase אשר לו asher lo repeats three times about the פר
par of Aaron and therefore we understand that kind of no matter
how we look at it, the שעיר sa'ir is for the people
and the פר par is for Aaron and the כהנים. kohanim. It
says משלו הוא מביא ואינו מביא משל ציבור. mishelo hu mevi ve-eno
mevi mishel tzibur. Phrase is necessary so to teach us that the
high priest brings the bull from him. So now what does he
have to pay for it?
He has to pay for it. That the
which is also very interesting, no, because the כהנים kohanim really don't
have money, so how do they pay for a thing?
The high priest always had money.
Huh? The high priest always had money. His own money?
He always had money.
His own money?
Yeah, of course. Like you know כהן גדול מאחיו, kohen gadol me-echav,
you know, and if he doesn't have money you give him money.
That's like the according to the גמרא Gemara like make him rich
if he doesn't if he's not rich.
Okay, so then it's like he has to use it from the
funds that he has, right? But the his funds that he has
he also got from other people. He doesn't have whatever property or
I'm sure he lived in a nice house despite not having a
חלק ונחלה. chelek vena'chala.
They're not gonna get some like shlub off the street to be
the כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. So משלו הוא מביא ואינו מביא משל ציבור, mishelo
hu mevi ve-eno mevi mishel tzibur, he can't bring it from the
community. יכול לא יביא משל ציבור שאין הציבור מתכפרים בו אבל יביא
משל אחיו הכהנים שאחיו הכהנים מתכפרים בו תלמוד לומר אשר לו. Yachol
lo yavi mishel tzibur she-ein hatzibur mitkaprin bo aval yavi mishel echav
hakohanim she-echav hakohanim mitkaprin bo talmud lomar asher lo. There is a
question of why this phrase אשר לו asher lo repeats in this
section three times. So each one of the times adds to our
understanding in
in why it must be his and why that atones for him
and the
כהנים. kohanim. יכול לא יביא ואם מביא כשר תלמוד לומר שוב אשר
לו הכתוב שנה לעכב. Yachol lo yavi ve-im mevi kasher talmud lomar
shuv asher lo hakatuv shanah le-akev. So the text repeats אשר לו,
asher lo, it must be his
in order to emphasize for us that this is for the כהנים,
kohanim, for him and for all the כהנים. kohanim. תנא הכי קא
קשיא ליה, Tana hachi ka kashya lei, what was the difficult? What
was the issue? מאי שנא דעם דלא מכפר דלא קא חסרי ביה
ממונא דכתיב אשר לעם.
Mai shna de-am delo mechaper
delo ka chasri be mamona dechtiv asher la-am. Here we go back
to the issue of the funding, who paid for it. So if
both mentions of the phrase his own אשר לו asher lo need
to teach us about the ownership of the bull then how can
the ברייתא baraita suggest that the phrase indicates that the bull atones
only for the high priest's transgressions? Right? Each one of them expands.
I'll read it to be this try to be correct throughout it.
Okay, if both mentions of this phrase his own, right, אשר לו
asher lo are necessary to teach about the ownership of the bull,
right, that it has to be his
then how can the ברייתא baraita suggest that the phrase indicates that
the bull atones only for the high priest's transgressions? If it was
only for him then maybe once would be enough. So from the
exclusion we understand that it's Aaron, from the repetition we understand that
it's Aaron, his household, the כהנים, kohanim, and that it must be
his. The גמרא Gemara explains. This is what was difficult for the
תנא, tana, right? תנא הכא קא קשיא ליה. Tana hacha ka kashya
lei.
What is different about the goat of the people that explains why
it does not atone, what is different question that explains... explains why
it does not atone for the priests. The difference is that the
priests did not forfeit any money over the purchase of it.
They have to pay for it. These
are all interesting ideas and there are nuances that we have to
pay for our atonement, you know, at the end of that funnel
of atoning for things. Therefore, huh?
No free lunch?
Yeah. Therefore, it does not atone for the priests, only for the
Israelites. That's the שעיר sa'ir that says אשר לעם. asher la'am. With
regards to the bull, to the פר, par,
the priests do not forfeit any money over the purchase of it,
so it follows that they should not achieve atonement. And therefore, to
explain why they do achieve atonement, it states 'his household'.
Okay? Yes. One more piece here. Okay. בשלמא לרבי שמעון, Bishlama le-Rabbi
Shimon, so that was explaining רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
So now back to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. היינו דכתיב תרי וידויים
ודם הפר, Haino de-chtiv trei viduyin ve-dam hapar, חד כנגד שעיר הנעשה
בפנים chad keneged sa'ir hana'aseh bifnim וחד כנגד השעיר הנעשה בחוץ ve-chad
keneged hasa'ir hana'aseh bachutz וחד כנגד שעיר המשתלח. ve-chad keneged sa'ir hamishtaleach.
So
for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he has a way to explain now
that there are two וידויים viduyim and the blood of the bull.
He's the one that holds that the שעיר sa'ir does not atone
for the people, so he can explain why there are two וידויים,
viduyim, two confessions and the blood of the bull. And how
does he break it down? This is what the people do with
one שעיר sa'ir inside, one goat that's sacrificed inside, one
outside, and one the שעיר המשתלח, sa'ir hamishtaleach, שעיר לעזאזל. sa'ir la-Azazel.
But for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, how would he explain the תרי
וידויים ודם הפר? trei viduyin ve-dam hapar? אלא לרבי יהודה תרי וידויים
ודם הפר למה לי? Ela le-Rabbi Yehuda trei viduyin ve-dam hapar lama
li? בחד וידוי ודמא סגי. Be-chade viduy ve-dama sagi. One וידוי viduy
and one whatever blood sprinkling should be enough. But then we
can explain it like this: אחד לו ואחד לביתו. echad lo ve-echad
le-veito.
Wait, why can't he say the same thing? One from the inside,
one from the outside, one the שעיר המשתלח? sa'ir hamishtaleach?
Because this שעיר sa'ir can't be counted, right? The שעיר sa'ir is
only for the people. So רבי... Rabbi... for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
he doesn't count the שעיר sa'ir as something that atones for the
כהנים. kohanim. So the וידויים viduyim has to be counted somewhere else.
I'm sorry, say it again, what does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
Wait, wait, backwards. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says two וידויים viduyim and
דם הפר dam hapar against the three שעירים se'irim that atone for
the people of Israel. רבי יהודה... Rabbi Yehuda...
Wait, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds what? That the... He doesn't hold
that it atones for the כהנים? kohanim?
Yes, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that the שעיר sa'ir does not
atone for the כהנים. kohanim. That was the conversation here in the
beginning of this session. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the שעירים se'irim
atone אשר לעם, asher la'am,
the whole people. I heard Rabbi Lentz saying yesterday how nice it
is, like the communal atonement that includes everybody. But רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon does not see it like that. He sees that the people
are atoned by the שעירים, se'irim, the כהנים kohanim have to be
atoned by the bull. Okay?
For him, the two וידויים viduyim and the blood of the bull
parallel the three שעירים se'irim of the people. For רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, who already kind of used the שעירים, se'irim, I think that's
what they mean, one וידוי viduy and one blood would be enough.
The גמרא Gemara answers the two confessions are necessary, one for the
high priest himself and one for his household, because it says 'his
own',
אחד לו ואחד לביתו. echad lo ve-echad le-veito.
Okay?
Completing this first chapter of שבועות, Shavuot, כדתנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל כך היא מידת הדין נוהגת. Kedetana de-vei Rabbi Yishmael
kach hi midat hadin noheget. This is how like the right thing,
how whatever how the justice functions. This is how it should be,
that's why they need two mentions of it. מוטב יבוא זכאי ויכפר
על החייב ואל יבוא חייב ויכפר על החייב. Mutav yavo zakai ve-yechaper
al hachayav ve-al yavo chayav ve-yechaper al hachayav. So Aaron has to
atone first, and once he's atoned, he's זכאי, zakai, he's clean, and
then he can atone for the others who were not yet atoned,
as opposed to the opposite where the people who have not yet
been atoned would atone for others. הדרן עלך שבועות שתים. Hadran alach
Shavuot shtayim. We have completed the first chapter in שבועות Shavuot and
moving on to the second one. Okay, in the second chapter, in
the opening of this second chapter, in this משנה, Mishna, we pick
up on something that we've discussed
briefly. שבועות שתים שהן ארבע, Shavuos shtayim shehein arba, ידיעות הטומאה שתים
שהן ארבע, yedi'os hatuma shtayim shehein arba, יציאות השבת שתים שהן ארבע,
yetzi'os ha-Shabbat shtayim shehein arba, מראות נגעים Nega'im שתים שהן ארבע. mar'os
nega'im shtayim shehein arba.
Okay.
So then we talked about שבת—we're Shabbat not talking about here because
שתים שהן ארבע shtayim shehein arba is going to be discussed in
מסכת שבת. masechet Shabbat. נגעים Nega'im. we're not talking about here
because it's going to be in נגעים. שבועות Shavuos we're going to
talk about later, chapter 3, 4, 5 and on.
And now the טומאה tuma we didn't quite explain. We talked about
the ידיעה. yedi'ah. We talked about the awareness and whether there is
an awareness in the beginning, at the end, where is the נעלם,
ne'elam, is the נעלם ne'elam in the middle, is it in the
beginning, is it at the end, is it in both parts?
But now we're going to break up what that means שתים שהן
ארבע. shtayim shehein arba. So let me read a little bit and
then I'll try to draw it in the chart and hopefully it
will become less cloudy.
ידיעות הטומאה שתים שהן ארבע.
Yedi'os hatuma shtayim
shehein arba. נטמא וידע ונעלמה ממנו הטומאה וזכר Nitma veyada venalma mimenu
hatuma vezachar. את הקודש ונעלם ממנו—option venalam mimenu one—וזכר את הקודש. vezachar
es hakodesh נעלם ממנו הקודש וזכר את הטומאה. Ne'elam mimenu hakodesh vezachar
es hatuma. נעלמו ממנו זה וזה ואכל את הקודש ולא ידע ומישאכל
ידע הרי זה בעולה ויורד. Ne'elmu mimenu zeh vezeh veachal es hakodesh
velo yada umisheachal yada harei zeh be-oleh veyored. Okay. Do you remember
or is this all like בלגן?
balagan? Okay,
let's do ידיעה. yedi'ah.
We
have two options of
ידיעה. yedi'ah.
Beginning or end.
העלם. He'alem. Okay, so we can have a ידיעה yedi'ah in a
beginning,
whatever, we spaced it, ידיעה yedi'ah at the end. Option one. Option
two: no ידיעה yedi'ah in the beginning, no ידיעה yedi'ah at the
end. We knew about it once but it escaped us and we
never recovered that knowledge. We had no idea in the beginning and
then somebody told us. And we have no idea and no idea
what's going on. Okay,
we are only in this top section. We're only here. Issues that
we knew. Okay.
נטמא וידע
ונעלמה ממנו הטומאה Nitma veyada venalma mimenu hatuma וזכר. So there's some
something that we know העלם he'alem and something that we know later
at the end and I'm going to chart it in a different
chart to explain how these two, four, six, eight unpack. Okay. נטמא
וידע ונעלמה ממנו
טומאה וזכר את המקדש, Nitma veyada venalma mimenu tuma vezachar es hamikdash,
נעלם ממנו
מקדש וזכר את הטומאה, ne'elam mimenu mikdash vezachar es hatuma, נעלם ממנו
זה וזה ונכנס למקדש ולא ידע ומישיצא ידע הרי זה בעולה ויורד.
ne'elam mimenu zeh vezeh venichnas lamikdash velo yada umisheyatza yada harei zeh
be-oleh veyored. Okay, you're ready?
All right, so what can we possibly know?
We can
know—we have that over
there. Well, oh, I see. קודש kodesh or מקדש mikdash right there,
variations.
Yeah, variations. I worked on this, give me a second. Okay. All
right.
Let's work through this together. Okay.
What can we possibly know? We can know that we have טומאה,
tuma, we can know that we are in the קודש, kodesh, we
can know that we're eating קודשים. kodshim. ידיעה. Yedi'ah.
Okay. If he possibly knows that he's
טמא—it's tamei not going to work, I'm going to need another one
here—he doesn't know that it's a קודש, kodesh, he doesn't know that
it's קודשים, kodshim, but he knows that he's
טמא. tamei.
You can have any of
these.
Any
combination. He doesn't know that he's טמא, tamei, he knows that he's
in the קודש, kodesh, he doesn't know that it's קודשים, kodshim, but
here is the ידיעה. yedi'ah.
He knows that he's טמא, tamei,
this is wrong then, right? That needs to be where
he knows he ate קודשים, kodshim, he doesn't, yeah.
Why
am I not impressed with my chart? Okay, what else am I
missing?
This and this?
Yes. Okay. He knows that he's
טמא, tamei, he knows
that it's... There's too many
X's.
Okay, we're gonna have to redo this. This was disappointing.
I'm not prepared for the דף daf at 11 o'clock at night.
Lesson of the day show. Okay, continue with the משנה. mishna. אחד
הנכנס לעזרה ואחד הנכנס לתוספת העזרה. Echad hanichnas la'azarah ve'echad hanichnas letosefet
ha'azarah. Okay, so if he walks into the קודש, kodesh, into the
עזרה, azarah, and what about somebody who walks to תוספת העזרה? tosefet
ha'azarah? And now the משנה mishna is gonna take a minute and
gonna talk to us about what does it mean תוספת העזרה? tosefet
ha'azarah? Why? Because, huh? Why?
That sounds like a very big digression as, it
is a digression, but I think maybe it's an important digression, you'll
see in a minute because,
okay, if you want to expand whatever it is, the city of
New York or the city of Tel Aviv or the city of
Haifa, I'm sure there's some way to do it. You just, whatever,
you have more people, you negotiate for some land, you move the
wall of the city, the fence, and,
and you're fine. But if you want to expand the עזרה, azarah,
like that place has to do with holiness. So how do you
add holiness to a place? You can't just come and say, hey,
we had a board meeting and we decided to buy six more
buildings,
and let's make a declaration that now it's holy, no pun intended.
אין מוסיפין על העיר ועל העזרות אלא במלך ונביא ואורים ותומים וסנהדרין
של שבעים ואחד ובשתי תודות ובשיר ובית דין מהלכין ושתי תודות אחריהם
וכל ישראל אחריהם. Ein mosifin al ha'ir ve'al ha'azarot ela bemelech venavi
ve'urim vetumim vesanhedrin shel shivim ve'echad uveshtei todot uveshir uveit din mahalchin
uveshtei todot achareihem vechol yisrael achareihem.
So we're gonna learn later on, we're gonna learn that there is
a process how to add things to the holy area of the
קודש, kodesh, and we need all these things: we need a מלך,
melech, a נביא, navi, אורים ותומים, urim vetumim, סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, full סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin, the תודות, todot, the offering of the bread,
a song, what kind of a תהילים Tehillim do we add, a
בית דין, beit din, and what do we do with the bread?
Like there's a process. We can't just come and say,
you know, this is now,
this is now קדוש. kadosh. Ritual? A ritual?
Yeah, yeah.
Which is an, like incredibly spiritual question. How do you add holiness
to a place? And what does it mean that a place has
holiness in it? What, what quality is there that
I can just go on
and on, later on, but, but past where we are today. Right
now we're still in this incomplete chart that I, I'm gonna sleep
on.
I think it's correct but I, I forget into it. Okay. All
right. הפנימית נאכלת והחיצונה נשרפת וכל שלא נעשית בכל אלו הנכנס לשם
אין חייב עליה. Hapenimit ne'echelet vehachitzonah nisrefet vechol shelo na'aseta bechol elu
hanichnas lesham ein chayav aleha.
Okay,
so continuing like the, the offering that we bring, right, the inner
fence offering would be eaten and the outer would be burned. This
is like part of the, the ceremony that will be described later
in the גמרא. Gemara. How do we add to the קודש? kodesh?
And if somebody has a transgression in an area that all these
things did not happen to it, אין חייב עליה, ein chayav aleha,
he's not, he's not liable because there's no קודש kodesh to it.
So therefore let's say if he was in a place where he
walked into a קודש, kodesh, but the location, it's as if like
the location didn't exist, right? This was not it, there was no
קדושה kedusha to the place, then he has no,
he isn't liable to be punished for doing
it. Okay. נטמא בעזרה ונעלמה ממנו טומאה וזכר את המקדש נעלם ממנו
מקדש וזכר את הטומאה נעלם ממנו זה וזה והשתחוה או ששהה בכדי
השתחויה או בא לו בארוכה חייב בקצרה פטור.
Nitma ba'azarah vene'elmah mimenu tumah vezachar et hamikdash
ne'elam mimenu mikdash vezachar et hatumah ne'elam mimenu zeh vezeh vehishtachavah o
sheshaha bichdei hishtachavayah o ba lo bearukah chayav beketzarah patur. Back to
this beautiful thing, let's see if this works. Okay. So the first
part of the משנה mishna discusses one that becomes ritually impure before
entering the temple and that's where the ידיעה yediya applies to. He
for some reason he touched something or he
was in some...
Okay, but now we're talking about what about a situation where he
was pure? The person is קדוש, Kadosh, he enters the temple in
a state of purity and afterwards
something happened, he touched something while he was already in, and then
this impurity was hidden from him, but he remembered, all of a
sudden he remembers that he's standing at the temple, or the fact
that he was standing at the temple was hidden from him, but
he remembered his טומאה, Tumah, or both facts were hidden, he had
a העלם He'alem about all of them. In all these cases, if
he does a השתחוה, Hishtachava, if he started his worship
or he stayed long enough in order to do a השתחוות, Hishtachavut,
right, in order to do this service, but he didn't actually do,
or he went the longer way, he's like, yeah, I felt maybe
a little bit of a טומאה, Tumah, but I'm in the temple,
I don't want to leave right now, take me forever to wait
in line and get back inside through all these stairs,
so then he's liable. If he just takes the short
route, בקצרה Biktzarah פטור, Patur, if he's just like oh my god,
whatever, I'm aware right this minute that I have some impurity and
I'm out of here, then he's exempt. But if he's like yeah
I have an impurity, let me find my way out of here
and he finds the longer way, then he's liable for this קרבן
עולה ויורד, Korban Oleh Ve-Yored, which is the sacrifice right here. This
is the קרבן עולה ויורד, Korban Oleh Ve-Yored, the sliding scale,
economically adjustable
קרבן Korban that he can bring. מצות עשה שבמקדש שאין חייבין עליה,
Mitzvat Aseh She-bamikdash She-ein Chayavin Aleha, this מצוה Mitzvah that a person
that is טמא, Tamei, that is ritually impure, must be sent out
of the temple as a positive מצוה, Mitzvah, and now the משנה
Mishnah is bringing us
something that is taught in another משנה Mishnah in הוריות, Horayot,
that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is not liable to bring an offering for
an erroneous ruling or a שגגה. Shgaga. A communal bull sin
offering is brought because of somebody doing a שגגה Shgaga that has
to do involving an action by somebody Jewish resulting from a שגגה,
Shgaga, from a mistake that's handed down by the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, so
it's about something very, very specific. But
this is the specific
description of the מצות עשה שבמקדש שאין חייבין עליה. Mitzvat Aseh She-bamikdash
She-ein Chayavin Aleha. Okay, what are the qualifications of it? If the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin
mistakenly ruled that one who became טמא Tamei while in the temple
may leave by way of a longer route, they do not bring
this offering,
but okay, we got it.
Okay, so then it will go to another offering and not the
קרבן עולה ויורד. Korban Oleh Ve-Yored. ואיזו היא, Ve-eizo Hi, now we
have a very specific situation that is mentioned in הוריות, Horayot,
this
is
מצות עשה בנדה שחייבין עליה, Mitzvat Aseh Be-niddah She-chayavin Aleha, it's a
specific issue that comes up with a נדה. Niddah. What happens? The
man was having relations with the woman and like everybody was
pure initially, but all of a sudden
while they were having relations, she experienced
menstrual bleeding, some form of טומאה, Tumah, and she says to him,
נטמאתי. Nitameti.
So
now he through her has the potential of being טמא. Tamei. When
she, this is like opposite than what we have with
the
מקדש. Mikdash. In the מקדש, Mikdash, as soon as the person realizes
that he's טמא, Tamei, he must leave right away, if he takes
the longer route and tarries along the way, then he's liable. With
the נדה, Niddah, opposite, if he removes himself from his intercourse... with
the woman, he—if he removes himself immediately, he is liable. And the
משנה Mishnah tells us מפני שיציאתו הנאה לו כביאתו. mipnei sheyetziato hana'ah
lo keviato. There's an understanding that there's a heightened pleasure by doing
so and therefore he should not leave immediately, he should wait until,
whatever, he doesn't feel like it anymore and then exit. And if
he doesn't do it, then he is liable.
So he's liable for a חטאת? chatas?
Yeah, for the bull offering for an erroneous ruling, which is a
very specific case right there.
And the other one is if tarrying in in the מקדש, Mikdash,
is that a חטאת chatas or a
variable offering?
I think it was—no, it is a sliding scale חטאת, chatas, קרבן
עולה ויורד. korban oleh veyored.
Okay,
so this was a detour.
So what did that last case have to do with the
סנהדרין's—what Sanhedrin
was—Because it's a case where somebody all of a sudden feels a
טומאה. tumah. I have to say, I don't completely get the situation
because they were in the מקדש Mikdash having relations? Like, what—I don't
get the full thing.
No, but I mean what was—was there an erroneous ruling by the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin
or not?
No, if the סנהדרין Sanhedrin mistakenly ruled that one may withdraw immediately,
they bring a bull offering for their erroneous ruling.
Oh, I see, thank you.
Okay, back to משנה. Mishnah. רבי אליעזר אומר, השרץ ונעלם ממנו, על
העלם שרץ חייב, ואינו חייב על העלם מקדש.
Rabbi Eliezer omer, hasheretz vene'elam
mimeno, al he'elem sheretz chayav, ve'eino chayav al he'elem Mikdash.
You know, it's like the sanctity of lovers, you know, the parallel
idea of being in the מקדש Mikdash and being inside, you know,
something like—you know what I mean? Okay, yeah, I
like
it because I always think there's more hidden things in the text
than we realize. And when we come across something that we feel
is like, oh, that's so crazy, what does that have to do
with anything, they knew what they were talking about and they had
like the full context. And
yeah, the
חסידיק Chassidic thing like this about, you know, one time there was
a fire and then there were only the logs and then there
was only the forest and we only have the story about the
whole thing. It's a little bit like this; we got a lot
less than what there was. Okay, so now back to—we're still in
the משנה, Mishnah, in the opening משנה Mishnah of פרק שני. perek
sheni. רבי אליעזר אומר, השרץ ונעלם ממנו, על העלם שרץ חייב, ואינו
חייב על העלם מקדש. Rabbi Eliezer omer, hasheretz vene'elam mimeno, al he'elem
sheretz chayav, ve'eino chayav al he'elem Mikdash. Rabbi Eliezer says, with regards
to this קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh veyored, if a person touches
a שרץ, sheretz, an impure thing, in whatever form that is, a
carcass of a non-kosher
animal or non-kosher whether domesticated or not domesticated or a creeping animal
or—and it was hidden. This is back to ויקרא Vayikra 5, the
opening of chapter 5 in ויקרא Vayikra that tells us about this
העלם he'elem issue, this this corner here, option one.
Then
okay, then the creeping thing, what happens? He's liable to bring this
offering
if the שרץ sheretz is נעלם ממנו, ne'elam mimeno, but for the
מקדש, Mikdash, not. גמרא Gemara is going to discuss some of it
later. רבי עקיבא אומר, ונעלם ממנו והוא טמא, על העלם טומאה חייב,
ואינו חייב על העלם מקדש.
Rabbi Akiva omer, vene'elam mimeno vehu tamei,
al he'elem tumah chayav, ve'eino chayav al he'elem Mikdash. רבי ישמעאל אומר,
ונעלם ונעלם
שתי פעמים Rabbi Yishmael omer, vene'elam vene'elam shtei pe'amim in this ויקרא
Vayikra chapter 5 in the opening, the word נעלם ne'elam repeats twice,
לחייב על העלם טומאה ועל העלם מקדש. lechayev al he'elem tumah ve'al
he'elem Mikdash. So
back back to this chart asset here. What exactly is one obligated
for? And we'll see that the גמרא Gemara is trying to unpack
some of it, like, do people—people are sort of expected to know
the טומאה tumah of the שרצים. sheratzim. So where again, where is
our liability, where is our knowledge beginning and ending? Okay, so the
verse states, back to the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thing, ונעלם ממנו
והוא טמא, vene'elam mimeno vehu tamei, it's hidden from him, from him
so that he's impure, right? This is in ויקרא Vayikra chapter 5.
It teaches that in a case one has a lapse of awareness
that he had contracted from touching a שרץ, sheretz, he— He's liable
to bring the קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh ve'yored, but one that
is not liable to bring such- one is not liable to bring
this kind of offering when the lapse of awareness has to do
with him being in the temple or the קדשים. kodshim. So, different
understanding about the שרצים, shratzim, and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says for
both. He's liable for both the העלם, ha'alem, the lapse of awareness
about the טומאה tumah and about the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay. Let's unpack
just a tiny little
bit.
אמר
רב פפא,
Amar Rav
Papa, let's see if we can do this. There's גמרא Gemara math.
Okay. By the way, you know, I had in my class that
I was teaching these ידיעות yediot on שבת Shabbat and we got
into a conversation, I just want to give credit to this being
part of a conversation, and somebody asked me, "Is this like an
age thing?" You know, first you have no awareness, then you have
some, then you have more, and then you have most awareness. And
so that system of four, I'm just putting it out if it's
useful for anybody, and if it's wrong, just erase it. It reminded
me, the combination of awareness and the number four, of the four
sons of the הגדה. Haggadah. So one that like doesn't even know
what to ask, one that is the תם, tam, one that is
the רשע, rasha, kind of he knew but then whatever caused him
to forget, and one that is the most knowledge. Could be wrong,
but that adds another
layer to those four sons that they really talk about a lot
more things throughout the גמרא Gemara because of this system.
The age thing goes in reverse also. The what? The age also
goes in reverse. Okay. Child becomes an adult, but when the adult
becomes old, it becomes like the child, starts to forget until he
doesn't have it anymore. I'm not applying it to that necessarily, I'm
just saying that, yes, it goes in both directions. Yeah.
Anyway, just something else to... Okay. Why? Why am I saying it?
Because the גמרא Gemara is going to do now a little bit
of גמרא Gemara math and let's see if we can stay with
it. Okay. אמר רב פפא לאביי שתים שהן ארבע שתים שהן שש
הויין. Amar Rav Papa le'Abaye, shtayim she'hen arba, shtayim she'hen shesh havyan.
You really, these two, right? The two options, really we have two
ways of knowing, either you know or you don't know. And then
there's permutations of these two, so that's two that are four. Either
you know מקדש קדשים, Mikdash Kodshim, you don't know, yes, מקדש קדשים.
Mikdash Kodshim. So that's two that are four. רב פפא Rav Papa
says to אביי, Abaye, no, it's really six.
I'm
not sure how he counts this. ידיעות הטומאה תחילה וסוף ידיעות הקודש
תחילה וסוף ידיעות מקדש תחילה וסוף.
Yediot hatumah techila vesof,
yediot hakodesh techila vesof, yediot Mikdash techila vesof. Okay. So we know
in the beginning, we don't know at the end, that's two.
And at the end, the first one is no- both, all of
them.
ידיעות, Yediot, just- I'll try to explain. The fact that we have
a ידיעה yediah in the beginning and a ידיעה yediah in the
end is two ידיעות. yediot.
Those two ידיעות yediot multiply times three. One time it can happen
with the state of impurity, one time it can happen with, I
don't know where I was, one time it can happen with, I
don't know what I was touching. Two times three: six. Yes. ולטעמך
תמני הויין. Uletamecha tamni havyan. Okay. Wait. אביי Abaye answers him, according
to your reasoning, if you count all these various cases, there should
be
eight. דהאיכא טומאה דקודש וטומאה דמקדש תחילה וסוף.
Deha'ika tumah dekodesh vetumah deMikdash techila
vesof. So now, let's see how we're going to open this up.
There's eight states of awareness, right? So there's also the awareness of
impurity in connection with eating the קדשים kodshim at the beginning and
at the end, awareness of impurity in connection with entering the temple,
beginning and end.
המשנה Hamishnah mentions the awareness of the impurity both in the first
clause with the קדשים kodshim and the second which discusses the temple.
So, I'm not sure, I don't know if these are the eight
or some variation of this. Okay. הלא קשיא. Hala kashya. That's not
a problem. Why did we think this was a problem? שם טומאה
אחת היא מכל מקום שית הויין. Shem tumah achat hi mikol makom
sheit havyan. This is, as a status of ritual impurities carries
one name in both cases, so this can be, there can be
a way to count it as eight or there can be a
way to count it as six. I like the six. ורב פפא
אמר לעולם תמני הויין. Verav Papa amar le'olam tamni havyan. There's actually
eight. There's four and four. Let's see what the four and four
are. ארבע Arba קמייתא qamayta דלא d'lo מייתי maiti לידי lidei קרבן
korban לא lo קחשיב. qahashiv. ארבע Arba בתרייתא batrayta דמייתי d'maiti לידי
lidei קרבן korban קחשיב. qahashiv. Okay, there's four.
Let's see where they are. Let me read this.
So there's two... Okay, so there's eight states of awareness. Let's see
if we count them. Two with the טומאה tumah in connection with
eating the קדשים. kodshim. We counted those. Two with the connection of
entering the temple. We got
those. Two...
okay wait a second. Eight awarenesses. Okay. Two with the impurity in
connection with the foods. Two with the impurity of the מקדש. mikdash.
Two awareness of the קדשים kodshim and two awareness of the מקדש.
mikdash.
So,
do you see how to
figure the eight? So there's maybe with the ידיעות yediot in the
beginning and the ידיעות yediot in the end and all these
permutations, each pair having one awareness in the beginning and one at
the end. So because there's four of each and each one has
an awareness in the beginning and at the end, then now there
is eight. But the first four states of awareness at the beginning,
they don't bring, they don't cause a liability if
the person doesn't have awareness at the end, right? We're going to
be in this category that there was no ידיעה yediah at the
end. If there was only an awareness of the beginning of the
טומאה tumah or the קודש kodesh or the קדשים kodashim and no
awareness at the end, he's not going to bring a קרבן. korban.
We have a situation where there is a קרבן korban at the
end.
So is he still liable when he becomes aware or...?
He counts them as part of the eight, but he doesn't count
the last
states where... we'll see, they'll reverse it immediately. There's four situations
that לא מייתין לידי קרבן. lo maitin lidei korban. The ones that
don't, that we're not liable to bring a קרבן korban for them
are not important, the ones at the end that cause us to
bring a קרבן korban are important. But then they reverse it. ואיכא
דאמרי אמר פפא לעולם תמני הוין V'ika d'amri amar Papa l'olam temani
havin and they're backwards. ארבע קמייתא דלא איתנהו בכל התורה כולה קחשיב,
ארבע בתרייתא דאיתנהו בכל התורה כולה לא קחשיב. Arba qamayta d'lo itanu
b'chol ha'Torah kullah qahashiv, arba batrayta d'itanu b'chol ha'Torah kullah lo qahashiv.
There are those that say that רב פפא Rav Papa said exactly
the opposite. There's eight states of awareness. The four states of awareness
at the beginning, which are not found in the entire Torah, just
here that the תנא Tanna was counting the just with the מקדש
mikdash and קדשים. kodashim. In all the other instances where one is
liable to bring an offering for a mistake, for a שגגת shigegat
transgression, it's not necessary that there will be any awareness in the
beginning.
So now the awareness in the beginning is not important, since it
is, this is a novel requirement, the תנא Tanna counts these states
of awareness. But he doesn't count the last four states of awareness
that
the standard sin offering is brought. Okay, so there will be atoned
by another offering after,
yes,
when one is aware that he transgressed then there's going to be
an offering brought.
A regular... he's not a variable, you mean?
Right, just
a regular, just a regular. So he's still responsible when he finds
out, right? And if he never finds out, then the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and the רגלים regalim and the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
atone. Okay.
Another problem we had just in the משנה Mishnah about the שרצים.
sheratzim. בעי רב פפא נעלמו ממנו הלכות טומאה, מהו? היכי דמי?
Ba'ei Rav Papa nelmu mimenu hilchot
tumah, mahu? Heichi dami? Okay, let's try to understand what we were
talking about, somebody doesn't know the הלכה halakha of טומאה tumah about
the שרץ. sheretz. רב פפא Rav Papa
shows us that there is a problem. אילימא דלא ידע דשרץ טמא
וצפרדע טמא? זיל קרי בי רב, Ileima d'lo yada d'sheretz tamei v'tzfardea
tamei? Zil krei b'rav,
like what, somebody doesn't know that a שרץ sheretz is impure or
a צפרדע tzfardea is impure? He should just go and learn it.
This is like, this is something that he should have learned in
grade school.
Ignorance of the law is not...
No,
especially of things that are for granted. לעולם דידע בטומאת שרץ, וכגון
דנגע ב... L'olam d'yada b'tumat sheretz, u'kegon d'naga b'... כעדשה ולא ידע
כעדשה היא מטמא לא מטמא
מאי k'adasha v'lo yada k'adasha hi metame lo metame mai okay רגע.
rega.
We're not exempting the person that didn't know that a שרץ sheretz
is טמא. tame. This is something that should be common knowledge, everybody
should know what it is. But what he doesn't know is what
kind of an amount
is okay to touch that
he might have touched,
and that is something that we can we can debate and we'll
see the גמרא Gomora is going to come to a case תיקו.
teiku. כיוון דידע דידע דמטמא שרץ בעולם ידיעה היא או דילמא כיוון
דכעדשה לא ידע אי מטמא אי לא מטמא העלמה היא תיקו. Keivan
d'yada d'yada d'metame sheretz ba'olam yedi'ah hi o dilma keivan d'k'adasha lo
yada i metame i lo metame ha'alama hi teiku. What is it
exactly that he didn't know? We don't accept that he doesn't know
שרץ, sheretz, a שרץ sheretz he should have known. Maybe he didn't
know the שיעורים. shiurim. He didn't know the amount of how much
he can touch. I'm going to close to honor our time. We'll
see that the conversation continues to discuss what if somebody didn't know
he was in the temple. And then the discussion is how can
somebody not know he's in the temple? They're like oh maybe he
came from בבל. Bavel. Ah maybe he came from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and it's not recognizable where exactly are the boundaries. Where
where is the line of knowledge so that we know how to
atone for that lack of knowledge so that we can go back
to our system of funneling טומאה tum'ah to טהרה taharah and atone
for what we need to atone. And with that, thank you for
being with us this morning and have a wonderful day. Thank you.